A Guide to the Records of HokiePRIDE, 1971-2015
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Records of HokiePRIDE, 1971-2015 (bulk 1995-2013)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
HokiePRIDE
RG 31/14/15
3.5 Cubic Feet 4 boxes, 1 folder, 2 oversize folders
The Records of HokiePRIDE include materials from the HokiePRIDE student group including items from all of its named iterations: Lambda Horizions; Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual Alliance; and Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Alliance, including officer papers, office records, event planning information, resource pamphlets and directories, and copies of budgetary requests and accounting records.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Access to unredacted HokiePRIDE Library circulation records is restricted. Contact Special Collections for more information.
Acquisition Information
The Records of HokiePRIDE were donated to Special Collections in 2016.
Historical Note
HokiePRIDE was originally founded in 1985 as Lambda Horizons (sometimes written as Lambda Horizon). In 1994, the group was renamed the Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Alliance (LGBA). Then, in 1999, the name was changed again to Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Alliance (LGBTA). In 2014 the name changed once more to the current name, HokiePRIDE.
HokiePRIDE was the second officially recognized LGBTQIA+ student group formed at Virginia Tech following the Gay Alliance of Virginia Tech (GAVT) in 1971. It also followed three unofficial groups: the Gay Liberation Front (GLF) in 1970, the Gay Student Union (GSU) in 1975, and the Gay Student Alliance (GSA) in 1976.
The early goals of HokiePRIDE included providing a place on campus for gay and lesbian members of the university community to meet without judgement, helping educate the campus community about homosexuality, and creating a positive image of gay and lesbian people. Over time, the group's mission expanded to include advocacy for everyone under the societally defined umbrella of LGBTQIA+, including bisexual, asexual, pansexual, transgender, and intersex people.
The group implemented multiple programs on campus to advocate on behalf of the LGBTQIA+ population including Gay Awareness Week, AIDS Awareness Week, National Coming Out Day, Freedom to Marry Day, Pride Week, advocacy for hate crimes legislation, and the organization of Safe Line, Safe Watch, the Safe Zone program, and more.
For more information on the current organization, see their website: http://www.hokiepride.org.vt.edu/
Scope and Contents
The Records of HokiePRIDE include materials from the HokiePRIDE student group including items from all of its named iterations: Lambda Horizions; Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual Alliance; and Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Alliance. The records consist of papers from the organization's officers, handbooks on programming and organizational operations for student groups, office records from the HokiePRIDE office and the original LGBT Resource Center (circa 2000s), event planning information, resource pamphlets, organizational marketing information, and directories that were available to visitors to the HokiePRIDE offices, and copies of organizational budgetary requests and financial accounting documentation. See the Arrangement note for additional information on the contents of the collection.
Arrangement
The records are divided into four sections reflecting the major groupings present when the records were received from HokiePRIDE. Folder titles are those supplied by HokiePRIDE for the majority of folders, especially those in the Office and Resource Center Records, and the Resources.
I: Officer papers, includes papers from the President, Vice President of the Interior, Vice President of the Exterior, Gay Awareness Week Chair, AIDS Awareness Week Chair, Webmaster, and Films Chair. It also includes applications for these positions and handbooks on programming and meeting materials from the Commission on Student Affairs meetings from 2008-2013.
II: Office and Resource Center Records, includes resource center sign-in sheets and library circulation records, copies of political action petitions, documentation of hate incidents on campus, Safe Zone materials, copies of the HokiePRIDE constitution, event planning documentation, event flyers, and more.
III: Resources, includes copies of various resources that were maintained in the HokiePRIDE resource center office for the use of members of the campus community. These include pamphlets and other documentation on a variety of sexuality and gender topics and organizational information for groups such as PFLAG, the Human Rights Campaign, the National Organization for Women, and the Roanoke Diversity Center.
IV: Finances, includes budget requests and accounting records for HokiePRIDE from 1995/1996 through 2014/2015 and budget requests for other student organizations from 2012/2013 to 2013/2014.
Separated Materials
The following materials were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Special Collections Rare Book Collection:
Appalachian Heritage, vol. 34, no. 3, Summer 2006
Soft Shorts by Anna Van Evera, 1992
Homosexuality and The Bible by Walter Wink, 1996
The following materials were removed from the collection and added to the University Archives:
The Bugle, 2002 (Virginia Tech yearbook)
Index Terms
Subjects:
Sexual minorities; University Archives; University History; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; LGBTQ history
- Series I: Officer papers, 1999-2014
  - Executive Board applications, 2012-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Contact information (officers), 2004-02-16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - President's papers, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vice President of the Interior's papers, 2008-2011 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Vice President of the Exterior's papers, 2004-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gay Awareness Week Chair's papers, 1999-2001, 2003-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Oversize 2, Oversize 3)
    Scope and Contents
    "Welcome Home" sign [Folder 2].
    "The Closet" sign [Folder 3].
  - AIDS Awareness Week Chair's papers, 2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Webmaster's papers, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Film Chair's papers, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Leadership retreat, c. 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - LGBTA Programming Handbook, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - LGBTA Programming Handbook, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - LGBTA Programming Handbook, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Commission on Student Affairs meeting materials, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Commission on Student Affairs meeting materials, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Commission on Student Affairs meeting materials, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Commission on Student Affairs meeting materials, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Commission on Student Affairs meeting materials, 2012-2013 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Commission on Student Affairs, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II: Office and Resource Center records, 1971-2015 (bulk 1995-2015)
  - Resource Center sign-in sheets, 2009-2010, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Resource Center library materials check out forms (Redacted), 2003, 2010, 2012-2014, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Resource Center library materials check out forms (Unredacted), 2003, 2010, 2012-2014, undated (Folder 1)
    Access Restrictions
    Access to unredacted HokiePRIDE Library circulation records is restricted. Contact Special Collections for more information.
  - LGBTA Office log books, 1999-2008 (1999-2003) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - HokiePRIDE List Serve sign-up sheet, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - LGBTA flyers, 2000-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs, 2006-2007, 2009-2010, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Resource Center, 2000, 2007-2008, 2012-2013, undated (Box 1, Folder 26, Oversize 2, Oversize 3)
    Pride Week poster [Folder 2].
    Gay rights timeline [Folder 2].
    Stop Spiritual Violence poster [Folder 3].
  - Political action petitions, 1991, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Hate documentation, 1995-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - April 16 condolence card from PRISM, Northern Illinois University's student LGBT organization, c. 2007 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Lambda Horizons newsletter, 1989-03-23 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - LGBTA newspaper clippings from the Collegiate Times, 2002-2008 (bulk 2002-2003) (Box 1, Folder 31, Oversize 2)
    Collegiate Times cover page August 29, 2008 (laminated) [Folder 2].
  - Constitution, 1971, 1985, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fundraisers, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Summer projects, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Workshop information, 1999-2000, 2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 2004 VA (Virginia) Out Retreat, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Student Organizations Showcase, 2000, c. 2005, c. 2015, undated (Box 1, Folder 37, Oversize 3)
    Trifold poster displays [Folder 3].
  - UUSA (University Unions and Student Activities), 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Human Rights Campaign's (HRC) National Coming Out Project, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - National Day of Silence, 2003-04-10 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Club Red Ribbon, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Safe Zones, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Event flyers, 1999-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Speaker contracts, 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Thank you notes, awards, and autographs, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Speaker catalogs, 1995-2002 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Movie catalogs, 2001-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Musicians, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Comedians and other performers, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Resources, 1988-2000
  - Religion, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Resources on Islam, Gender & Sexuality, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bisexual Resources, 1992, 1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lesbian Rights, c. 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Coming Out, c. 1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Family Diversity, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Health / Health Supplies, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gender Issues, 2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Heterosexual Infomation, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Same-Sex Marriage, 2004, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Roommate Problems, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hate Crimes, 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Counseling, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Domestic Violence, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Safe Sex, 1990, 2009, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Health Care Reform, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hispanic / Latino, 1999-2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Other Pages, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Women's History Project, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG), undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Pride in the Park Roanoke, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Shenandoah Valley Gay and Lesbian Association, 1998-05 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lesbian Services Program, Whitman-Walker Clinic, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - South Eastern College Conference for LGBT Students (SEC Conference), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - GLBT Campus Conference, 1997-04-12 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Advocate, 2000-12-14, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - AIDS Quilt, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Blue Ridge Lamdba Press, 1999-September/October (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Gay & Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Gender Public Advocacy Coalition (GenderPAC), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Human Rights Campaign (HRC), 1999-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Lambda PTO: Employee Organization for the Patent and Trademark Office, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Millennium March on Washington, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force (NGLTF), 1989-2000 (bulk 1995-1996) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW), 1999-2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Pride Events (national), 1992, 1994, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Progressive Action Network (P.A.N.), undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Multicultural Awareness Programs (MAPs), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Valley AIDS Network (VAN), 2006 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Roanoke Diversity Center, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - JQ International, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - The Roomer, newsletter of Residential & Dining Programs at Virginia Tech, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Silhouette, Virginia Tech's Student Literary Magazine, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Sexual Assault and Violence Education and Services (SAVES), 2000-02-07 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Series IV: Finances, 1995-2015
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2011-2012 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2012-2013 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2013-2014 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Budget Requests and Accounting Records, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Budget Requests for other student groups, 2012-2014 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - University Chartered Student Organizations (UCSO) Funds Handling Policy, 2012-2013 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Oversize materials, c. 2005, 2008, c. 2015, undated (Oversize 2, Oversize 3)
  "Welcome Home" sign [from Box 1, Folder 6: Gay Awareness Week Chair's Papers].
  "The Closet" sign [from Box 1, Folder 6: Gay Awareness Week Chair's Papers].
  Pride Week poster [from Box 1, Folder 26: Resource Center].
  Gay rights timeline [from Box 1, Folder 26: Resource Center].
  Stop Spiritual Violence poster [from Box 1, Folder 26: Resource Center].
  Collegiate Times cover page August 29, 2008 (laminated) [from Box 1, Folder 31: LGBTA Newspaper Clippings: Collegiate Times].
  Trifold poster displays [from Box 1, Folder 37: Student Organizations Showcase].